-==破烂熊乐园倾情奉献==-
本字幕仅供学习交流，严禁用于商业用途
归来记
-==http://www.ragbear.com==-
福尔摩斯探案全集 第3季第1集
-=Keepfrds MNHD Team=-
校对: ptrpan
1981年 莱茵辛巴赫瀑布
In 1891 the Reichenbach Falls
瑞士马灵顿
near Marlington in Switzerland,
福尔摩斯夏洛克终于和莫里亚蒂教授
Sherlock Holmes finally closed his
决一死战
account with Professor Moriarty,
莫里亚蒂是当时最危险的罪犯
the most dangerous criminal of his generation.
两个人在险要之地单独决斗
The two men were alone in that dreadful place
但是结果
but the outcome of their struggle
正如如人人所料
was obvious to a trained observer.
福尔摩斯击败了
Holmes had achieved the destruction
他的死敌
of his archenemy,
而他自己也付出了生命的代价
only at the cost of his own life.
空屋
从我亲爱的朋友去世
It is now three long years
已经过去漫长的三年了
since my dear friend plunged to his death.
在那漩涡激荡的无底深渊中
There deep down under the swirling water
当代最危险的罪犯莫里亚蒂教授
the infamous Professor Moriarty
和当代最杰出的护法卫士
and the foremost champion of law of his generation
将永远长眠在那里
will lie together for all time.
即使现在
Even now,
伦敦的每一个角落
there is hardly a corner of London
都会令我忆起自己的老朋友
that does not remind me of my old friend.
我再也未曾踏足贝克街
I never walk down Baker Street
因为我们一起在那里渡过的日子里
where we shared rooms
经历了无数惊心动魄的案件
for so many eventful years
能让我脑海总是浮现出
without it reminding me
过去的往事
only too keenly of the past
还有那位我认为是
and the loss of one I shall ever regard
世上最优秀聪明的人
as the best and wisest man I have ever known.
我仍对刑事案件
I retained a keen interest
保持着浓厚的兴趣
in criminal matters
通过做警局的法医
and supplemented my meager practice
来补充匮乏的消息来源
by working as a police surgeon.
那是1894年的早春
It was in the early spring of 1894
我一大早便应约
that I was called out early in the morning
前往西郊
to an appointment in the west end.
早上好 警官
Good morning Constable.
早上好 医生
Good morning Doctor.
雷斯垂德警探正等你呢
Inspector Lestrade is waiting for you,
二楼 先生
first floor sir.
谢谢
Thank you.
警探?
Inspector?
一大早的麻烦你了
Early call I'm afraid Doctor.
很高兴见到你
I'm glad to see you.
那可是尊敬的罗诺德・阿德尔
The Honorable Ronald Adair.
请不要放在那里
Not there sir if you please.
抱歉
I'm sorry.
23岁
Age twenty-three,
梅鲁斯伯爵夫妇的
the second son
次子
of the Earl and Countess of Maynooth,
他父亲是澳大利亚某殖民地的总督
father is governor of one of the Australian colonies,
他母亲冬天住在伦敦
mother in London for the winter,
儿子和女儿
son and daughter
和他一起住在这房子里
are living in this house with him.
自杀?
Suicide?
不是
No.
没有发现武器
No weapon.
呃 还有这个
Oh uh, this.
这个是在尸体旁的地板上发现的
This found on the floor beside the corpse.
一颗软弹头的左轮枪子弹
It's one of those soft nose revolver bullets,
可怕的东西
horrible things.
肯定是直接打穿了
Must have gone right through
可怜的罗诺德的脑袋
the poor fellows head.
不同寻常 不是吗
It's unusual, isn't it,
一把手枪竟然有这么大的威力
for a pistol to have such velocity?
更像是一把来福枪
More like a rifle.
没错
Yes.
应该是谋杀 警探
Well it's murder then Inspector.
是的
Oh yes.
有没有什么推断?
Any idea who it was?
没有
No.
现在为时尚早
It's early days yet
但这个案子
but this one looks to me
看起来像是
as if it could turn out to be
谜团重重
a bit of a puzzle.
假设他当时
Well presumably he was
坐在那把椅子上
sitting in that chair.
我想他正在数钱
I suppose counting that money.
杀人者不可能
Oh the murderer doesn't appear
是个小偷
to have been a thief.
阿德尔整晚
Adair had spent the evening
都在俱乐部打牌
playing cards at his club.
准备好最后一搏了
Time for one last hand?
是的 当然
Oh yes indeed.
终于可以复仇了
Now we can get our revenge.
谢谢
Thank you.
罗纳德 你下多少赌注呢?
Now Ronald, what's the damage?
罗纳德?
Ronald?
我想罗纳德
I don't think Ronald
不可能又出去了
couldn't have gone out again.
是的 夫人
No my lady.
我听到他大约十点半回来的
I heard him come home at about half past ten.
之后没有再出去
And he hasn't gone out again,
我很确定
that I'm sure.
罗纳德先生?
Mr. Ronald?
罗纳德先生
Mr. Ronald sir.
我去撞开门吧 夫人
Let's break it down my lady.
从尸体的姿势来看
From the condition of the body
死亡发生在一瞬间
death was instantaneous.
我想杀人者
I suppose the murderer
是从窗户进来的
came in through the window.
窗户是开着的
The window was open.
同样的问题是
Same spot of the matter is
没有任何侵入者的痕迹
there are no signs of any intruder,
什么都没有 屋内外都没有
nothing, inside or out.
我可不想大半夜从这里爬上来
I wouldn't like to climb up here at night.
只有猴子才能做得到
It must have been a monkey.
正如你所说 那是不可能的
As you say Doctor, an impossibility.
好像杀人者长了翅膀一样
Looks like the murderer had wings.
这种案子我们的老朋友
Sort of case that would have interested
福尔摩斯肯定会很感兴趣的
our old friend Mr. Sherlock Holmes.
绝对的
Yes indeed.
多么大的损失啊 医生
What a loss he is Doctor.
我不经常用他的理论
I didn't always approve of his methods
但他是私人侦探中最棒的
but he was the best amateur there was
空前绝后的
or ever likely to be.
有几次
There were times when
他做的甚至比我还棒
he even got the better of me.
好了 警探
All right, Inspector,
你该把他
if you arrange for our friend
送到太平间去了
to be brought down the mortuary
我下午会去验尸的
I'll conduct an autopsy this afternoon.
好的 医生
Yes indeed Doctor.
到时候再见
See you at the inquest.
回见
Till then.
西敏市皇家法庭
(该市是大伦敦地区一个次级行政区域  伦敦自治市)
华生医生
Doctor Watson,
你是警局的法医
you are a police surgeon?
是的 法官
Yes sir.
你检查了已故的
You examined the deceased,
罗纳德・弗朗西斯・阿德尔
Ronald Frances Adair,
本案受害人的尸体
who is the subject of this inquest
随后对其
and later conducted
进行了尸检?
a postmortem on the corpse?
是的 法官
I did sir.
那么你有什么发现?
Prey what are your findings?
死亡原因是
Well death occurred
子弹造成的创伤
as the result of a bullet wound
由一颗0.45口径的左轮手枪子弹引致
from a point four-five revolver.
华生医生?
Dr. Watson?
请你紧贴事实
I beg you to keep to fact.
我的责任是确定
My business is to establish
本案的事实
the facts of this case.
抱歉 法官
I'm sorry sir.
我不明白您的意思
I don't understand.
你说子弹来自一把
You say that the bullet
0.45口径的左轮手枪
came from a point four-five revolver
那纯粹是你的个人推断
that is pure speculation on your part.
你没有责任妄自猜测
It is not your business to start guessing
凶器的型号
at the type of weapon used.
这属于警局的职责范围
That is a subject for the police.
抱歉 法官
I'm sorry sir.
那么继续吧
Prey continue.
受害人死于致命创伤
Death occurred as the result of a wound
该伤口由一颗软弹头铅弹造成
from a soft-nosed lead bullet.
子弹从左眼上方的
The bullet penetrated the skull
头骨穿入
above the left eye,
贯穿左前脑叶
traversing the left frontal lobe
击穿小脑
through the cerebellum
最后经由左后脑腔骨缝
and then exited from the skull
穿出头骨
at the back of the head
从后脑勺射出
by the left occipital parietal suture.
以你之见
In your opinion,
死亡过程持续了多久?
when did death take place?
应该是瞬间死亡
Oh it would have been instantaneous.
你可知道
Have you any idea
击中受害者之前
how far this bullet had traveled
飞行了多长距离吗?
before it entered the body?
不太确定
I cannot be sure
但可以确定的是
but it would certainly be
至少在四五英尺之外
more than four or five feet.
死亡时间呢?
Time of death?
死亡发生在10:30至11:30之间
Death occurred between 10:30 and 11:30
本月20号午后
post meridian on the twentieth of this month.
谢谢 医生...
Thank you Doctor...
华生
Watson.
罗纳德・阿德尔和我一起打板球
Ronald Adair and I played cricket together.
他是个一流的击球手
He was a first-class bat,
脚下很灵活迅速
pretty effective leg spinner.
很好的运动员 是吗?
A good sportsmen, in fact?
一流的运动员 法官
Absolutely first class sportsman sir.
修长挺拔
Straight as a dime.
我认识的最受欢迎的人之一
One of the most popular fellows I know.
谢谢 穆雷先生
Thank you Mr. Murray.
约翰・哈代爵士
Sir John Harvey.
我是罗纳德・阿德尔的教父
I was Ronald Adair's godfather
以及财产托管人
and a trustee of the estate.
毫无疑问 他的家人已经被
Of course the family's absolutely devastated
他的惨死所击垮
by this appalling tragedy.
我带他一起玩惠斯特(牌类游戏)
I put the boy up for the Bagatelle Cup
实际上
as a matter of fact.
他很喜欢打牌
He always he enjoyed the game of cards.
不论输赢吗?
Win or lose?
输赢会不会影响
Would that affect Mr. Adair
阿德尔先生的心情 约翰伯爵?
in any way, Sir John?
法官大人 一点也不会
Lord no, not in the least.
他从来不会因为输钱
He never paid such high stakes
而影响到自己的心情
that could affect him at all.
他的家境
The family fortune
非常富裕
is a very considerable one.
谢谢 约翰爵士
Thank you Sir John.
您帮了很大的忙
You have been a great help
像你这么德高望重的人
and may I say that evidence from such
所提供的线索
a distinguished person, as yourself,
对我们来说相当有价值
is greatly valued by the court.
莫兰上校
Colonel Moran.
你是最后一位
You were the last person
与阿德尔先生见面的人
known to of seen Mr. Adair.
你很了解他吗?
Did you know him well?
我不敢说很了解他
I wouldn't say that I knew Ronald Adair well.
但我和他爸爸梅鲁斯伯爵很要好
I knew his father, Lord Maynooth, very well.
我们以前在印度
We used to play
经常一起打马球
polo together in India
但是罗纳德
but Ronald.
我经常在俱乐部里看到他
I've seen quite a good bit in the dark clubs
过去几个月以来
over the past few months
我们不时在一起
we played cards together
玩牌
from time to time.
英俊的小伙子
Oh charming boy.
礼貌 聪明
Good manners, intelligent.
实际上
Matter of fact,
他是年轻人的楷模
he's just the stamp of a young fellow
我倒是希望能他进我以前的军队
I'd like to see joining my old regiment.
你注意过他有什么反常吗?
Did you notice anything unusual about him?
他是不是很担忧或者不高兴
Did he seem worried or upset
就在那你见到他的最后一晚?
on the last evening you saw him?
一点也没有
Not in the least.
实际上正好相反
Quite the opposite in fact.
你是否想到
Have you any idea why
谁有可能谋杀他?
someone should choose to murder him?
想不出来
No idea at all.
我觉得他根本没有仇人
I doubt if he had an enemy in the world.
谢谢你 莫兰上校
Thank you Colonel Moran.
雷斯垂德巡官
Inspector Lestrade
能不能谈谈你对
would you give me your opinion
罗纳德・阿德尔死因
as to the cause of the
有什么看法?
Honorable Ronald Adair's death?
好的 法官
Yes sir.
被熟人或不认识的人
Willful murder by person
蓄意谋杀
or persons unknown.
马车
Cab.
"被熟人或不认识的人"
Willful murder by person
"蓄意谋杀"
or persons unknown.
马车 来这边
This way, cab.
去肯辛顿
Let's go to Kensington, carriage.
什么事?
Yes?
一位先生想见您
A gentleman to see you Doctor.
是急事吗?
Is it an urgent matter?
不知道 先生
I don't know Doctor.
他有给你名片吗?
Well did he give you his card?
没有 先生
No Doctor.
艾维 我告诉过你
Ivy if I've told you once
我说过无数次了
I've told you hundred times,
我的询诊时间
my consulting hours are
在外面清清楚楚的挂着呢
plainly displayed outside.
现在去...
Now please...
先生
Oh sir.
华生医生?
Doctor Watson?
是我 先生
Yes indeed sir.
你可以走了 艾维
You may go levy.
我现在很忙 先生
I am exceedingly busy sir.
当然 你是医生嘛
Oh of course you are Doctor.
你是个通情达理
Of course you are a man of
富有责任心的人
considerable responsibilities
我听说你把自己的地址
but I heard you give your address
给了法庭外面的马车夫
to that cab driver outside the courtroom.
我对自己说
I said to myself
我一定要去见见
I'll just hobble around
这位好心的人
and see that Kind gentlemen,
我觉得有点过意不去
I have a conscious.
刚才有点粗暴
I felt a little gruff in my manner
我没有恶意
I meant no harm by it
我其实很感激他
I'm much obliged to him
帮我捡起了书
for helping me pick up my books.
你把这事想得太严重了
You make too much of a trifle sir.
应该去度个假 放松一下
You should have spared yourself the journey.
如果不太冒昧的话
Now if you'll excuse me.
我没空度假
No great journey sir.
我算是你的街坊
I am a neighbor of yours.
你肯定看到过我的小书店
You will find my little bookshop
就在教堂街的拐角处
on the corner of Church Street.
很高兴见到你
I'm very happy to see you
我确定...
and I'm sure that...
大概...你也收藏书吧...
perhaps... you collect...
我这儿有《英国鸟类》
I have British Birds
珍藏本的《圣战》
quite a rare volume of The Holy War
每本都很便宜
bargains every one.
刚好可以填满
Just the books you need
你书架上的空挡
to fill up your bookcase.
让它更有分量
Give it a little weight.
现在看起来不大整齐 不是吗?
It does look untidy, does it not?
华生 介意我在你的询诊室里
Watson, do you mind if I smoke a cigarette
抽根烟吗?
in your consulting room?
万分抱歉 亲爱的华生
A thousand apologies my dear Watson.
我一点也没想到你会如此经受不住
I had no idea that you would be so affected.
福尔摩斯!
Holmes!
真的是你吗?
Is it really you?
难道你还活着?
Can it really be that you're alive?
你真的觉得现在有精神谈这事了吗?
But are you really fit enough to discuss things?
瞧我这多此一举的戏剧性的出现
I have given you a serious shock
给了你多大的刺激
by my unnecessarily dramatic reappearance.
不 不 不
No, No, No,
我好了
I'm all right.
我没事
可是 福尔摩斯
But indeed, Holmes,
我不敢相信我的眼睛
I can hardly believe my eyes.
世界上那么多人
Good heavens, to think that you
单单会是你
you of all men-
站在我的房间里
should be here in my consulting room.
不管怎么样 你不是鬼
Well you're not a spirit at least.
亲爱的朋友
My dear chap,
看到你我太高兴了
I'm overjoyed to see you.
坐下 坐下
Sit down, sit down
告诉我你是怎样
and tell me how you came alive
从那可怕的峡谷中逃生的
out of that awful chasm.
很高兴能伸直腰
Oh I'm glad to stretch myself.
让一个高个子一连几个小时
It's no joke when a tall man
弯腰驼背
has to take a foot off his stature
可不是件轻松的事
for several hours on end.
我亲爱的老朋友
Now, my dear fellow,
还有一个晚上的
we have a hard and dangerous
艰险工作等着我们
night's work ahead of us.
或许最好是
Perhaps it would be better
等这项工作完了以后
if I gave you an account of the whole situation
我再把全部是情况告诉你
when that work is finished.
不 不 不
No, no, no.
我很想知道
I'm full of curiosity.
更喜欢现在就知道
I should much prefer to hear now.
今晚愿意跟我一起去吗?
But you will come with me tonight?
随你说什么时候
When you like,
去什么地方都行
where you like.
哈!
Ha!
华生
Watson.
真的还像过去那样
This is just like the old days.
我们出发前还有时间
We might have a chance for a mouthful of dinner
吃点晚饭
before we need go.
当然 晚饭
Dinner of course
但你得先告诉我所有的事
but first you must tell me everything.
你确定没关系吗?
You sure you're all right?
是的 我很好
Yeah, I'm fine.
好吧...
Well then...
说说那个峡谷
about that chasm.
我要爬上来
I had no serious difficulty
根本没有什么难度
in getting out of it,
因为很简单
for the very simple reason
我根本就没掉进去
that I was never in it.
你根本没掉进去?
You were never in it?
没有 华生
No, Watson.
我根本没掉进去
I never was in it.
可是我在莱辛巴赫瀑布
The note that I left on the rock
给你留的便条
at the Reichenbach Falls
完全是真的
was absolutely genuine.
我一点也不怀疑
I had little doubt
我的末日到了
that my career had come to an end
当我发现邪恶的莫里亚蒂的身影
when I perceived the somewhat sinister figure of Moriarty
就站在狭窄的走道上
standing upon the narrow pathway
那条窄道通向安全地带
that led to safety.
在他灰色的眼睛里我看到了邪恶的意图
I read an inexorable purpose in his gray eyes.
我得到他的同意
I managed to obtain his courteous permission
写下了一张便条
to write the note,
就是你后来看到的那张
which you afterwards received.
我将它视若珍宝 好好保存着
It has remained my treasured possession.
直到几个月后
It was a few months later
我津津有味的读到了
that I read with great interest
你对我的死的描述
your description of my death.
写得很好
It was excellently done,
充满生动
the most picturesque
而刺激的想象
and exciting piece of fiction.
当然 我发自内心的高兴
Well I'm certainly glad
因为我写的
from the bottom of my heart
并没有发生
that it was fiction,
可是究竟发生了什么?
but what did really happen?
当我走到岩架
When I reached the ledge
我站在峭壁边
I stood at bay.
他并没有掏出武器
He drew no weapon,
而是冲了过来
but rushed at me
用他颀长的胳膊抱住我
and threw his long arms around me.
他知道一切都完了
He knew that his game was up.
只急着报复我
He was only anxious to revenge himself upon me.
但是 我懂得一些日式摔跤
I have, however, some knowledge of baritsu,
或者说是柔道
or the Japanese system of wrestling,
过去好几次我都用上了这一手
which has on more than one occasion,
非常管用
been very useful to me.
天啊
My God.
可是...你是怎么从那里逃生的?
But... but how did you get away from that place?
那可不是件让人高兴的事
It was not a pleasant business.
就在莫里亚蒂掉进深渊时
Even as Professor Moriarty disappeared into oblivion
我突然想到命运给我安排了绝佳的机会
it struck me what an extraordinary lucky chance
安全近在眼前
Fate had placed in my way.
但我知道至少
I knew that at least
还有一个莫里亚蒂的余党
one of Moriarty's henchmen
想置我于死地
would seek my demise now.
这念头因为他们主人的死
With even keener determination
变得更加强烈
to revenge their dead leader
我想最好让全世界都相信
but if I could convince the world
我也一同丧命
that I too was dead,
所以我决定
so I decided
消失
to disappear
就在那一瞬间的决定
then and there.
老天爷啊
Heavens above.
但那些足迹呢? 福尔摩斯
But the tracks Holmes?
我亲眼所见
I saw them with my own eyes.
两个人的足迹通往下面 没有回来的
Two went down the path and none returned.
我不是个富于幻想的人 华生
I'm not a fanciful person Watson,
但一点不假
but I give you my word
好几次 当我往上爬时
there were times during that climb
仿佛听见莫里亚蒂的声音
when I seemed to hear Moriarty's voice
从深渊中
screaming at me
冲我喊叫
from out of the abyss.
最后 我爬到了一个地方
At last I reached a place
没有被人发现
where I was able to remain unseen.
福尔摩斯?
Holmes?
在那个隐蔽的地方
From my concealed place
我看着你们
I watched you and your followers
充满怜惜
investigate in the most sympathetic
却毫无效率地勘察
and inefficient manner
我丧生之地的环境
the circumstances of my death.
最终你们都意见统一
At last, when you had all formed your
做出了完全错误的判断
inevitable but totally erroneous conclusions,
然后你离开了
you departed.
是该上路的时候了
It was time for me to be on my way.
当然 这意味着什么就很清楚了
Of course, the meaning of this was obvious.
莫里亚蒂不是一个人来的
Moriarty had not been alone.
他的一个余党
A confederate
在远处目睹了
from a distance had been witness
他朋友的灭亡和我的逃脱
to his friend's demise and my escape.
我的思考没有耽搁多少时间 华生
I did not take long to think about it, Watson.
我拼命的跑
I took to my heels
在山里摸黑前进
and covered ten miles
逃出了十英里
over the mountains in the pending darkness.
一周后
A week later
我到了佛罗伦萨
I found myself in Florence,
确定这世上
with the certainty that
没有人
no one in the world
知道我的下落
knew what had become of me.
我只有一个可以信赖的人
I had one confidant-
我哥哥迈克罗夫特
my brother Mycroft.
我必须告诉他这事
I had to confide in him
为了得到我需要的钱
in order to obtain the money I needed to live.
当然
Of course.
我得再三向你道歉 华生
I owe you many apologies, my dear Watson,
但是当时最重要的是
but it was all-important
让人们相信我已经死了
that it should be thought I was dead,
你要是不相信我死了
and it is quite certain that you would
也肯定写不出一篇令人信服的
not have written so convincing an account
关于我不幸结局的
of my unhappy end
感人故事来
had you yourself not thought that it was true.
我几次要提笔写信给你
I have taken up my pen to write to you,
但总害怕
but always I feared
你对我的深切关心
lest your affectionate regard
会让你不慎
might tempt you to some indiscretion,
泄露秘密
which would betray my secret.
我还以为
I would have thought
我和你哥哥一样值得信任呢
I was as trustworthy as your brother.
你当然是 华生...
Of course you are Watson...
但是你更加善良
but you have a kinder heart.
可是你这些年都在做什么
But what have you done all these long years?
你也许看到过
As you may have read
一位名叫西格森的
of the remarkable explorations
挪威探险家的考察报告
of a Norwegian called Sigerson,
但我保证你从没有想到过
but I am sure that it never occurred to you
你看到的
that you were receiving
是你朋友的见闻
news of your friend.
是你
You?
我在西藏
For two years I traveled
游历了两年
to Tibet
常以去拉萨
and amused myself by visiting Lhasa
和大喇嘛聊天消磨时光为乐
and spending some time with the head Lama.
之后我又去了波斯
I then moved to Persia,
到喀土穆(苏丹首都)对哈里法(伊斯兰教国家领袖)
and paid a short but interesting visit
做了简短而有趣的拜访
to the Khalifa in Khartoum,
并把拜访的结果
the results of which I have passed on
交给外交部的凯彻姆部长
to Lord Ketchum in the Foreign Office,
当然 是匿名
anonymously of course.
你是说你亲眼见到了皇宫
You mean you actually saw the palace
戈登被谋杀的地方
where Gordon was murdered?
凄惨的场景
It was a sorry sight.
他的血还残留在夹克上
His blood still upon his jacket.
最近我去了法国蒙特利尔
Lately I've been in France in Montpellier,
研究煤焦油的衍生物
to research the coal tar derivatives.
这时候发生了这件惊人的谋杀案
Then came the news of this remarkable murder,
案件的离奇吸引了我
which not only appealed to my by its own merits,
似乎给我个人带来了
but would seem to offer some most peculiar
最难得的机会
personal opportunities.
我立刻回到这里
So here I am.
你来过贝克街
Have you been to Baker Street?
是的
Yes.
今天早上 我自己打了个电话回去
I called there this morning in my own person.
迈克罗夫特把我屋子
Mycroft had preserved my rooms
和文件原模原样保存着
and my papers exactly as they had always been.
就这样
So it was,
我发现自己
that I found myself
回到了我的老房间里
in my old rooms,
坐在原来的椅子上
sitting in my old chair,
满心希望能见到
and only wishing that I could have seen
我的老朋友 华生
my dear friend, Watson
也坐在对面的
sitting in the other chair
他一向常坐的椅子上
which he has so often adorned.
我正是这样希望的
And so I hope I will be.
多么值得非凡的故事啊
What... what a remarkable story.
你的左轮手枪
Are you still in possession
还在吗?
of your Army revolver?
应该还在
Well I think I have it somewhere.
确保你晚上带在身上
See that you bring it with you tonight.
我给咱俩安排了一点工作
I have piece of work for both of us
如果咱们能成功的
which if we bring to a successful conclusion,
结束它
will in itself
就不枉活在世上
justify a man's life on this planet.
求求你讲详细点
I beg you to tell me about it.
天亮前够你听和看的了
You will see and hear enough before morning.
华生
Watson?
我能占用一会儿你的病床吗
May I occupy your couch for a few hours?
海上的航行极其艰苦
The sea was exceeding rough
穿过海峡时
during the channel crossing
又一次看到伦敦
and the prospect of seeing London again
还要和一个莫里亚蒂的余党
and an intimate encounter
进行一场激烈的决斗
with one of Moriarty's confederates
加上将要看到
plus the added pleasure
老朋友华生的兴奋
of seeing my old friend Watson
而之后在火车上
quite prohibited sleep
辗转反侧难以入眠
on the railway train.
亲爱的 福尔摩斯 拜托
My dear Holmes, please,
你可以睡我的床啊
my bedroom is at your disposal.
不 不 不
No, No, No.
这个挺舒服的
This will suit me very well.
过去的几年里
I've had harder beds than this
我睡过比着还硬的床呢
over the past few years.
知道我们在哪吗?
Do you know where we are?
当然 那是贝克街
Surely that is Baker Street.
说对了
Exactly.
但这间空屋
But in the empty house
正对着我们的房子
opposite our old quarters.
为什么要来这里?
Why are we here?
因为从这里可以清楚的
Because it commands such an excellent a view
看到对面的楼
of that picturesque pile.
麻烦你 华生
Might I trouble you, Watson, to be so kind
靠窗户近一点
as to draw a little nearer to the window,
小心别暴露自己
taking every precaution not to reveal yourself,
再看看我们的房间?
and then to look into our old rooms?
让咱们看看我离开这三年
Let us see where the three years of absence
是不是完全失去了
have entirely taken away my power
让你惊奇的能力
to surprise you.
天哪!
Good heavens!
妙极了
It's marvelous.
我相信我变化多端的手法尚未因
I trust that age doth not wither nor custom stale
岁月流逝而枯竭
my infinite variety.
的确有几分像我 是不是?
It is rather like me, is it not?
我可以发誓说那就是你
I should be prepared to swear it was you.
功劳归于
The construction is due to
格勒诺布尔的
a Monsieur Oscar Meunier,
奥斯卡莫尼埃先生
of Grenoble.
那是一座蜡像
The bust is in wax.
其余是今天下午
The rest I arranged
我在贝克街自己布置的
during my visit to Baker Street earlier.
但是为什么?
But why?
因为我有最大的必要
Because I have the strongest possible reason
让某些人相信
for wishing certain people to believe
我在那
that I was there
其实我并不在那
when I was really elsewhere.
你认为有人在监视你的房子?
You thought the rooms were watched?
我知道有人在监视
I knew that they were being watched.
是谁?
By whom?
那可爱的一帮人里
By the one remaining member
仅剩的一位宿敌
of that charming society
他们的头子此刻正躺在莱辛巴赫瀑布下面
whose leader lies in the Reichenbach Falls.
他相信早晚
Sooner or later he believed
我会回来的
that I would come back to my rooms.
所以派人不断进行监视
So he had them watched continuously.
今早他们看到我到达伦敦
I was observed when I arrived this morning.
我看到了放哨的人
I recognized the sentinel.
姓巴克尔
Parker by name,
以杀人抢劫为生
a garrotter by trade,
是个出色的犹太口琴演奏家
and a remarkable expert Upon the jew's-harp.
现在我明白
Now I understand the reason
你为什么要扮成老书商了
for the old bookseller.
我不在乎巴克尔
I cared not about Parker
但我非常担心
but I care a great deal about
他背后那个
the much more formable person
更加难对付的人
who is behind him,
莫里亚蒂的把兄弟
the bosom friend of Moriarty.
今晚在追我的正好是他
That is the man who is after me tonight
但我们相信
and let us hope that he is also the man
他并不清楚
who is totally unaware
其实是我们在追他
that we are after him.
福尔摩斯
Holmes
看!
look!
就在楼那边
Just beyond the house.
门口那两个人影
Couple of shady characters in the doorway.
是的 我看到了
Yes I see them.
我们是不是该做点什么?
Well shouldn't we do something?
不
No.
福尔摩斯
Holmes,
影子动了
the shadow's moved.
当然会动
Certainly it has moved.
我让哈德森太太这么做的
I involved Mrs. Hudson.
我们在这里待了两个小时
We have been in this room two hours
她已经把蜡像的位置
and she has made some change
变动八次了
in that figure eight times,
每一刻钟换一次
or once every quarter.
福尔摩斯先生
Mr. Holmes.
雷斯垂德 见到你太高兴了
Lestrade how nice to see you.
真的是你?
So it really is you?
我接到你的信时
When I received your message
几乎不敢相信
I could scarce believe it.
我觉得你需要点非官方的帮助
You seem to want some unofficial help.
一年中有三起谋杀案
Three undetected murders in one year
破不了是不行的
won't do you know.
福尔摩斯 我认识这个人
Holmes I know this man.
你当然认识 华生
Of course you do Watson.
警探先生也认识
So does the Inspector.
赛巴斯蒂恩・莫兰上校
Colonel Sebastian Moran,
以前在女王陛下的印度军中效力
once of Her Majesty's Indian Army,
咱们东方帝国造就的
and the best heavy game shot
最优秀的射手
our Eastern Empire has ever produced.
我相信我说的没错吧 上校
I believe I'm correct, Colonel,
你的猎虎绝技
in saying that your bag of tigers
仍然是举国无双吧?
still remain unrivalled?
奇怪 我这么简单的计策
I wonder that my simple stratagem
就能让一个老狐狸上当
could deceive so old a shikari.
你不是也经常
How many times have you not tethered
在一棵树下栓只小羊
a young kid under a tree,
自己带着来复枪躲在树上
laid above it with your rifle,
等着你的诱饵
and waited for your bait
把老虎引来吗?
to bring up your tiger?
这间空屋就是我的树
This empty house is my tree,
你就是我的猎物!
and you're my tiger!
同样的方法
The parallel is exact.
你可能有或者没有
You may or may not
逮捕我的正当理由
have just cause for arresting me
但至少没有理由
but there can be no reason
让我受到
why I should be subjected
这个人的嘲弄
to the jives of this person.
如果我现在在法律掌握中
If I'm in the hands of the law
都一切照法律办吧
let things be done in a legal way.
你说的倒是很合理
Well that sounds reasonable.
走之前 你还有什么要讲的吗?
Anything further to say before we go?
只有一个问题
Only to ask
你要以什么罪名提出控告?
what charge you intend to prefer?
什么罪名 先生?
What charge sir?
当然是企图谋杀
Why of course the attempted murder of
福尔摩斯夏洛克先生了
Mr. Sherlock Holmes.
这不成 雷斯垂德
Not so Lestrade.
这么出色的逮捕是你的功劳
To you, and to you only, belongs the credit
只属于你一个人的功劳
of this remarkable arrest.
以你惯有的智勇双全
With your usual mixture of cunning and audacity
逮到了他
and you have got him.
我不明白 福尔摩斯先生
I don't understand you Mr. Holmes.
抓住了谁?
Do you mean this man?
这就是整个警局
The man whom the entire police force
一直都没有找到的
has been seeking in vain
赛巴斯蒂恩・莫兰上校
Colonel Sebastian Moran,
是他杀害了年轻的阿德尔
who shot the young Adair
上个月20号在阿德尔父母的房子外
through the open window of his parent's house
透过敞开的窗户射杀了他
upon the twentieth of last month.
这就是罪名 雷斯垂德
That is your charge Lestrade.
你真是这个案子的女英雄 哈德森太太
You were quite the heron of the occasion, Mrs. Hudson.
可能是因为我很矮吧
Why I don't know, I'm short.
一切预防措施你都遵守了吗?
I hope you have preserved all precautions?
是的 先生
Oh yes sir.
我跪在地上爬过去
I went to it on my knees
就像你告诉我的一样
just exactly as you told me
我背上的疼痛可以证明
and a good crick in my back to prove it.
我害怕极了 医生
Oh I was frightened Doctor
当窗户碎掉的时候
and when that window shattered
我以为我要死了
I thought I should have died.
你做的棒极了 哈德森太太
Yes you did it very well Mrs. Hudson.
没有子弹的影子
There's no sign of the bullet.
抱歉 先生
Excuse me sir,
帮我拿一下
a moment if you please.
什么事?
What is it?
子弹在我这儿
I have it here.
我从地毯上捡起来的
I picked it up off the carpet.
你真是帮了大忙
Mrs. Hudson you are becoming indispensable.
一个软弹头铅弹
A soft revolver bullet,
正如你们所见
as you perceive,
多么巧妙啊
there's genius in that
谁会想到
for who would expect such a thing
这会是从一把气枪里射出的?
to be fired from an air gun?
这可不是一把普通的气枪
It's no ordinary air gun.
绝对不是
No indeed.
非凡而独一无二的武器
Remarkable and unique weapon.
威力巨大却没有声音
Noiseless and of tremendous power
我认识这个・范哈德
I knew Von Herder
盲眼的德国技工
the blind German mechanic
这把枪是他给
who constructed it to the order of
莫里亚蒂教授特制的
the late Professor James Moriarty.
华生 看啊
Watson look at this.
老猎人居然
The old shilkaris nerves
还手不抖
had not lost their steadiness
眼也不花
nor his eyes their keenness.
惊人的准头
The results are appalling.
是的
Yes indeed.
在阿德尔被谋杀前
Have you heard of the name Moran
你听过莫兰这个名字吗?
before Adairs murder?
没听过
No I had not.
是啊 是啊 是啊
Well, well, well,
这就叫出名
such is the price of fame.
请你从书架上
Would you be so kind to hand me
把L到M开头的
on my L-M index?
传记索引拿来?
Our biographies Watson?
我收集的M部分材料很不错
My list of M's is a fine one.
莫里亚蒂这个名字不论在哪
Mind you Moriarty's name is enough to make
都是最出众的
any letter illustrious.
我记得好像还有
I seem to remember
投毒犯摩根
Morgan the poisonner.
遗臭万年的梅里丢
Merridew an abominable memory.
还有马修斯
And there was Mathews,
他在查林十字车站
who knocked out my left canine
打掉了我的左犬牙
in Charing Cross Station.
最后是我们昨晚见到的老朋友
Awe there is our friend of last night.
赛巴蒂斯恩・莫兰上校
'Moran, Sebastian, Colonel.
原系英国驻波斯公使
Son of Sir Augustus Moran,
奥古斯都・莫兰爵士之子
once British Minister to Persia.
曾就学于伊顿公学 牛津大学
Educated Eton, Oxford.
参加过乔瓦基和阿富汗战役
Served in Jowaki Campaign,
在舍普尔 喀布尔
Afghan Campaign, Sherpur, Cabul
服过役
mention to dispatches.
伦敦第二号最危险人物
The second most dangerous man in London.'
真叫人惊奇 福尔摩斯
This is astonishing Holmes.
这人还是个体面的军人呢
This is the career of an honorable soldier.
确实是的
It's true.
他在一定程度上干得不错
Up to a certain point he did well
但是有一些树
yet there are some trees, Watson,
在长到一定高度时
which grow to a certain height
会突然长成
and then suddenly develop
难看的古怪形状
some unsightly eccentricity.
这一点常常会在人身上看到
You will often find it in humans.
不管出于什么原因
Whatever the cause,
莫兰开始堕落
Moran began to go wrong.
虽然没有什么丑闻
Without an open scandal,
但仍然在印度呆不下去
he still made India too hot to hold him.
他退伍了 回到伦敦
He retired, came back to London
又弄得声名狼藉
but again he acquired an evil name.
这时候
It was about this time
他被莫里亚蒂教授看中了
that he was sought out by Professor Moriarty.
在瑞士时 华生
When you were in Switzerland, Watson,
莫兰和莫里亚蒂一直跟着我们
Moran followed us with Moriarty
毫无疑问
and it was undoubtedly he
是他给了我莱辛巴赫悬崖上
who gave me those evil five minutes
那不愉快的五分钟
above the Reichenbach Falls.
现在我明白你为什么要消失了
Well now I can understand why you disappeared.
有这么一个自由的危险人物
With a fellow like this, free in London,
很可能性命不保
your life would not have been worth living.
我所能做的就是等待
All I could do was wait
并留意犯罪新闻
and watch the criminal news
我知道如果耐心等待
knowing that if I was patient
他早晚会露出破绽
sooner or later he would make a mistake.
当我听到罗纳德・阿德尔被谋杀的事
When I heard of the murder of Ronald Adair
我知道我的机会来了
I knew that at last my chance had come.
我确定
Knowing what I did
这明摆着
was it not certain
是莫兰上校干的
that Colonel Moran had done it.
他先和这个年轻人打牌
He played cards with the lad
随后从俱乐部跟踪他到家里
followed him home from his club
从开着的窗户
and shot him
射杀了他
through the open window
就在对面的房顶上
from the rooftop opposite.
华生还有什么
Watson does anything else
需要我解释的吗?
remain for me to explain?
是的
Yes.
你还没说清楚
You have not made clear
莫兰谋杀
what was Moran's motive
罗诺德・阿德尔的动机是什么
in murdering the Honorable Ronald Adair.
这一点我们只能推测了
There we move into the realms of conjecture.
各人可以根据证据做出
Each may form his own hypothesis
他自己的假设
upon the present evidence,
而你我的假设都有可能是正确的
and yours is as likely to be correct as mine.
华生 你已经有假设了?
Watson have you formed one?
我想是的
I think so.
让我听听
Let me hear.
我想说明案件的事实并不难
Well it's not difficult to explain the facts.
本案显然是
There must have been
牵涉到一笔可观的金钱
a considerable amount of money involved
莫兰作了弊
and Moran had undoubtedly played foul.
我想阿德尔发现了
I think that Adair had discovered
莫兰在作弊
that he was cheating.
非常好
Splendid.
很可能他私下跟莫兰谈过
Very likely he spoke to him privately
还恐吓要揭发莫兰
and threatened to expose Moran unless he
除非他自动退出俱乐部
voluntarily resigned membership in his club
并答应从此不再打牌
and promised not to play again.
华生 太棒了
Watson this is excellent.
开除出俱乐部
Exclusion from his club
就等于毁掉了
would mean ruin to Moran,
靠打牌骗钱为生的莫兰
who lived by his ill-gotten card gains.
因此
Therefore,
他杀了阿德尔
he murdered Adair.
这样可以吗?
Will it pass?
毫无疑问
I think, without doubt,
你说到点子上了
that you have hit upon the truth.
这会在审讯时得到证明
Anyway it will be verified
或是遭到反驳
or disproved at the trial.
同时 不论再发生什么
Meanwhile, come what may,
莫兰上校不会再打搅我们了
Colonel Moran will trouble us no more.
冯赫德尔这支了不起的气枪
And the famous air gun of Von Herder
将为苏格兰场博物馆增色不少
will embellish the Scotland Yard Museum.
进来
Come in.
再次 福尔摩斯
Once again Mr. Sherlock Holmes
可以自由的献身于
is free to devote his life
调查伦敦
to examining those
错综复杂的生活引起的
interesting little problems,
大量的有趣的小问题了
which the complex life of London
多么好的礼物啊
so plentifully presents.
福尔摩斯先生
Mr. Sherlock Holmes.
破烂熊字幕组
-==http://www.ragbear.com==-
欢迎加入